But instead
very beginning when you wake up in the
morning you know that this is not an
ordinary day. Every performance is a
most important performance. The pressure
is high. It has to look good. It has to
sound good.
What I'm trying to do is to avoid human
contact before you're saving your
energy.
This is where you forget that. This is
where the music takes over. We start
with a litany with a prayer and we end
with an orgy. It is a perfect [music]
circle.
I'm dealing with the greatest geniuses
in human history and playing their
music.
Every little bit in this puzzle has to
work.
It also needs to fly. It needs to be
something that people forget about
everything by listening to this concert.
[cheering]
People
are afraid to like explore the different
varieties of music out there. Like you
want to just stick to what you know. You
have to try it. And if you don't like
it, okay, that's fair. It's something
that you don't like, but you can't just
go around just saying like, "Oh, I don't
like classical music." And I ask you if
you've listened to it and you say no.
Cuz like, how do you know that? Music is
a like a key
and the life is a is a door. Yeah. So
use the music to open the door.
>> People base life off of something along
the lines of a popularity contest. So
they're going to tend to go with the
trend. So not so much they don't have an
appreciation appreciation for classical
music, just that they're not exposed to
it enough to have an appreciation for
it. This music is filled with really
human themes about love and poverty and
struggle and everyone can relate to
those themes. It really is a universal
language. What's great about classical
music and what it often can do is that
it can reach you personally
in a deep way that sometimes other music
cannot.
>> I think music is a language. It's a way
that people can speak to each [music]
other through eras, through
countries, through cultures, and I think
that's a really important part of the
human experience.
>> I still remember the time in 2002 in St.
Petersburg where a cup of coffee was $4
and a a philarmonic ticket was $2.
Concerts were sold out and people went
because it was arrested. It was a s sort
of a sanctuary um and a way to escape
from you know the tough realities of
everyday life.
>> It once was popular music. [music]
Italian operas were the equivalent of
today's pop music. This music had some
core of beauty and profoundity in it
that has meant that human beings have
held on to it.
Music and art is part of
of being a human being. Every generation
from the beginning of time, uh there's
music and art. It's the unique thing
about what makes us human.
Music is part of our life. We should
really treasure it.
It is beginning and the end of
everything for me.
The word itself is related um
edetmologically to to something having
to do with magic. A master has this
magical power to create something. It's
a function of love and intensity. You
love what you're doing and the number of
hours that you put into it.
We started studying music and playing
practicing piano since since I were five
five years old or something like that.
And of course I went sang in a boy
choir, practiced piano. I took violin
lessons. I remember so well my family
having dinner. There was always music
playing in the background either on the
radio or on the record or a cassette
tape. And so while we were talking, he
was always listening to music as well.
And in the middle of the most heated,
most interesting moment of the of the
debate or a conversation, my father was
like, "Sh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait,
listen, listen."
And we all listened. My mother was
always saying, "Okay, we listen now.
kind of get back to the conversation.
But for him, [music] there was
absolutely no way that anything was more
important.
When we arrived in Kennedy Airport,
[music] I remember
getting into this car. I've never seen a
highway in my life before. eight lanes
of just car lights
and you thought,
"How am I ever going to be found here? I
will disappear and never be noticed ever
again." I come from a country of 1 and a
half million people. There are more
people on that highway than in my entire
country.
>> Well, here in New Jersey, we have a man
who is already becoming world famous for
his mature approach to conducting. Yet,
he's only 20. Pabo Yurvy from Ruters.
>> Three years ago, their desire for
artistic freedom brought the Yervy
family from Soviet Estonia. His father
still looms large in Pavo's musical
thinking. [music]
>> The reason I'm studying conducting and
why I'm so interested in conducting is
because of um my father's example.
When I came to this country,
I went to Juliet pre-ol
and graduated it with one year. This
summer, Pavo is off to study at a very
exclusive conducting workshop in Los
Angeles.
He walked in quite old already and then
he stood on the podium to demonstrate
something for the students and [music]
he became a teenager. He was jumping up
and down. He was, you know, amazingly
physical and emotional expressive.
you realize that
how much he knew. We were sitting at
somebody's
apartment. Bernston was there and
somebody put on a record
was a Brahm symphony
and everybody tried to identify what it
was, which performance it was. And we
were all sort of trying to show off our
knowledge. Well, it sounds like this and
sounds like that.
And we were listening to the the the the
surface, [music] you know, first time
was of listening to the listening and
I hear
I hear war.
And sure enough, it was a Fangler
recording
in 1945 when actually the bombs were
being dropped in Berlin in and it was
one of those moments when I just
realized, okay, I can't even hear
the essential things in music because
I'm so busy and preoccupied with all the
peripheral stuff.
Love and time equals mastery. If you
love what you're doing, if you love
music, you'll put in those proverbial
10,000 hours. And at a certain point, as
they've demonstrated scientifically,
you're going to reach a level where your
brain is operating on another plane. And
that you will you will naturally reach
mastery.
I've seen students struggle with the
competition and you know this this
school has a lot of prodigies but but
everyone is here for a reason because
everyone especially have something to
say
walking into this school and being in
that school. It's a parallel universe.
>> Curtis was founded in 1924 by Mary
Louise Curtis Bach. She had this vision
to create a small conservatory
of the greatest young musicians on the
planet. It is the hardest school to get
into in the United States of any kind.
These students are a little bit like
Olympic athletes and they train in the
same way. I mean, complete commitment.
Everyone here is on full tuition
scholarship. based purely on merit. And
everyone shares some common experiences.
And [music] one of those experiences is
even just the struggle to get into the
school.
You know, I came from Florida and in my
town, [music] I was the best pianist in
the area. It was easy to feel a little
comfortable. And when you come here,
everyone is coming from their own
country or [music] place being the best.
It makes you have to realize that
there's something bigger, you know,
music, music is bigger than all of us,
really.
>> We moved here a year later, my mom and
I. [snorts] And uh she made a big
sacrifice because she spent two years
here while I was still in high school
away from my dad. He had to hold down
the fort in [music] Louisiana. And uh so
it was a difficult two years for them
just cuz they're over a thousand miles
apart.
>> I can't imagine which way my life would
have been if I didn't go there.
Classical music's a very competitive
marketplace.
>> You cannot possibly respond to all these
inquirs and you cannot possibly go to
all of these uh showcases. So most often
you go and hear someone because you've
already been hearing about that person.
There's more talented musicians of a
consmate skill than ever before and the
skill level gets higher and higher.
>> I'd love to be the music director of a
major orchestra or a major opera
company. I just want the opportunity to
work with the best of the best on a
consistent basis [music] and know that
every night um on the podium I have a
chance uh to create a great concert um
that serves my colleagues and that
serves the community that I'm a part of.
In the beginning, you try to convince
each orchestra, doesn't matter how small
or big, that you are a good conductor.
And if you convince them sufficiently,
they will invite you back.
When I first um conducted Cincinnati
Symphony, I remember just arriving here
and and being in the downtown
Cincinnati.
The downtown was pretty depressing,
frankly, at that time. Then I went to
the rehearsal and
after the first rehearsal I thought
there's something going on here
because it was amazing. Just the way
they played, the kind of [music]
attitude there was, the the quality,
something just was right.
The baton of maestro Pavo Yarvey
gracefully leads for the last time in
Cincinnati.
>> It's the final farewell for the music
director of the Cincinnati [music]
Symphony Orchestra.
One interesting thing is that people can
play without a conductor. They don't
need the conductor to play their [music]
parts. And that's something a good
conductor realizes as well.
>> There are an infinite number of choices
that a conductor makes in in realizing a
score. Subtle variations of tempo,
[music]
subtle changes in dynamic levels,
pushing and pulling against the beat.
And [music] every conductor does
something differently. There's there's
it's impossible to play a piece the same
way.
Seeing the interaction between the
conductor and the 80 people up there. I
mean, it's amazing. Get 80 people all to
play together at the at the same time.
That's an incredible thing if you think
about it.
>> That's what a great leader or conductor
can do. He can bring everybody onto the
same page, unite all the egos and people
[music] with their own agendas.
>> A conductor is like a coach in rehearsal
and like a quarterback during
performance. A conductor is the
mastermind [music] behind the score. He
is channeling the composer's intention.
>> Conductors are really the interpretation
of the score.
>> It's a story about being a person, about
being human. Every composer writes about
their daily lives, but also about their
hopes and dreams.
>> Practice makes things automatic and it
frees your mind up to think on a higher
level.
>> You always study. I study on airplanes.
I study whenever I have a day off. I
study when I come back from a
performance. You come home, you open the
score and you start looking at things.
I feel like whatever I do on stage, he
reacts to. It's almost like when you're
having a conversation with someone and
they understand [music] where you're
coming from. I'll play something and
I'll have a a new idea on stage that
I've never tried before. he's never
heard me do and he knows exactly what
I'm going to do somehow even before I've
ever done it before and he's right with
me on it. He isn't just a company. He's
really contributing
>> on the macro level is understanding the
whole really understanding where
everything fits together and the overall
structure of the piece and the pacing of
everything. And that's something that
maybe not every [music] orchestra member
knows or will have thought about where
their part fits in to everything to
really make it come off in the in the
best possible way. You're the boss. You
know, it's knowing how to handle people
to have all those skills in one person
is is is very rare and that's why
there's so few conductors, great
conductors.
>> Already from the name we are being
misled. There's nothing classical and
you can go from medieval music which is
also characterized as classical music to
20th century music that is minimalist
[music] music like John Adams and or
Philip Glass and it's also called
classical music.
>> It's almost like a great uh coach in a
for a sport. A conductor who doesn't
have to be so technically brilliant at
playing the violin has all of this
experience and all the different people
they've had to deal with over the years.
They have learned so much.
Bleman is an amazing place. It is a home
of what I think is [music] one of the
great chamber orchestras maybe in the
world. One of the great things about
this orchestra is the self-governing
completely independent democratic way of
making their everyday decisions. They
don't work for anybody else. They own
the orchestra.
>> Music is is communication between
people. Um it's not an order given from
one to the other. Very many conductors
give you orders. Parvo communicates with
you. Um he shares jokes.
>> By the way, this is my biggest
>> [laughter]
>> I have many fans.
>> They are a self-governed orchestra. They
are a very strong family to begin with
and they choose their their their
conductors. They choose their
management. It's
>> because the musicians are owners of the
orchestra. They are shareholders. They
are reliable not only for the notes they
deliver on stage. They are as reliable
for the figures in the uh balance
sheets. I feel that I am much more
[music] than just a conductor. I'm a
fellow musician. I'm I'm I'm part of the
family.
There's a very little rehearsal time
sometimes and and The mister or the
conductor needs to make sure everyone
knows as fast as possible who's the
boss. Po is great. The sort of authority
you need in in in this situation comes
extremely naturally to him. He doesn't
need to sort of make believe that he's a
different kind of person.
>> A great creative, a great musician, a
great conductor, a great composer, they
not only are technically brilliant, they
have a feel for what I call the spirit
of the times, the zeitgeist. and how to
take all of their knowledge from the
past and transform it into something new
and on a much higher level.
>> Culture is everything. Culture is the
quality of food. Culture is quality of
architecture. Culture is music. Culture
is words. Culture is everything.
Everything. Being being being alive.
It's culture.
>> Your main job as conductor is to inspire
[music] those who are playing for you.
You know, inspire them to really dig
deep into the score and find all this
beautiful inner meaning. It's one of
those only countries that you can go at
4:00 in the afternoon where you just
want to eat and you go to a bar and
there are people elderly people.
This is and it is sort of surreal and
it's really beautiful in many ways.
[music]
It's all about reacting. It's all about,
you know, going with the flow and
understanding where you fit in and and
and understanding [music] when you have
a part that needs to be prominent and
when you have to lay back. An orchestra
in many ways is like a sports team.
Everybody [music] contributes. Everybody
has to know exactly what their place is
and what their duty is and how they fit
in. An orchestra needs to be unified to
be seen as an orchestra. So you need the
same clothing. So what do you do? You
either wear all black shirts or you wear
tails.
>> Like a good team. An orchestra that
respects and likes each other always
will play better.
>> That's why he comes up and gives me the
hand that's kind of symbolizing that
he's shaking everybody's hands.
>> When the concert maker shakes my hand,
he's reminding me of the trust that
exists.
It's a symbol. They need to give
absolutely everything from themselves.
>> We always have to be careful not to be
too reverent towards the past. Tradition
is a great thing, but also a very
dangerous thing because if tradition
makes you feel like, well, this is the
way it's always done, that means you're
not going to find anything new.
Occasionally, we invite local students
to come to the rehearsals. It's
something we look forward to and it's a
good test. If we can't keep [music]
their attention, we know we have to try
something different.
>> I played the bass since uh I started
with um 11.
>> I was 6 years old and I wanted to play
the violin because I saw my grandfather
playing the violin
>> when I was 3 years old. I was always in
youth orchestras.
>> I even started with the cello when I was
four,
>> eight, maybe seven. Um, which so well
you can subtract seven from 21 and find
out how long I've been playing. No gray
hair.
>> We learn from the previous generation.
We just don't suddenly born from the
womb and know how to speak English.
That's the moral obligation. Passing on
your knowledge, your expertise, your
feel for for what you do and your love
of what you do to the next generation.
The effect that music has on on children
in so many ways is um is mindboggling.
It helps their social skills. It helps
their math skills. It helps integrate
all aspects of life. It all comes
together in music and art.
>> Bringing this music to children, they
are expanding [music]
uh those students understanding of what
human civilization can be. We should
make the argument based on beauty alone.
That to not know this music is to be cut
off from
one of the greatest sources of human
expression,
love, tragedy, suffering, and ecstasy
that humans have developed. It helps so
much like to have something to go to
when you're upset because whenever
someone makes me upset, I just go
downstairs and I just practice and I
practice until like I feel like more
calm and able to handle whatever
situation.
>> I discovered something inside myself
that I never knew I had. I came to
realize that music in my times of
sadness or my times of happiness, it's
always there. That's how I feel. I feel
like music is always there for me.
>> Classical music is special. It's really
special. It's like a bird fly on the
sky.
>> There's a sense of history that I feel
um is sometimes lost in our current
generation. We're we're sort of live in
the moment generation, you know, and uh
if we just know the music that's the pop
music that's playing today and just read
the books that are on the top 20
bestsellers of the time, we don't
understand anything about where it came
from and where we came from. Somebody
has to open a door
for you and say, "Okay, listen. Come
with me. Listen to this. What do you
think of this?
I spend most of my life on tour. This is
where I feel most comfortable.
For an independent [music] orchestra
like this, tours are crucial. They
create revenue, attract fans, and keep
our reputation alive as one of the best
orchestras in Europe.
>> If we make the wrong decisions, [music]
it might go downhill the whole thing.
This all makes us more close.
When you're a young orchestra, an
unknown orchestra, young conductor,
[music] you have to prove yourself. The
more exposure you have, a better track
record you have.
It's called reputation, the more
difficult it gets for us because
there is so much more pressure [music]
in trying to live up to all the things
that you are expected to live up. Like
all humans, we can have a a bad day. We
can have a difficult concert. We can
things sometimes [music] don't click.
You know, things happen. It is just a
very human thing. We're not robots.
So that the pressure to remain in good
shape, to be as good basically on every
level is even
more pronounced.
On tour, we stick to strict schedule.
The moment we arrive, we go straight to
the rehearsals. There is no time to
waste. Tensions are high.
Mediocrity is the enemy.
Music doesn't allow for mistakes.
When we get to this place, this place
don't get the joint so it doesn't get
>> when you go on stage. There is a
entirely different set of laws. You need
to be as relaxed as possible.
>> A concert day from the very beginning
when you wake up in the morning, you
know that this is not an ordinary day.
Around 2:00 or so, I I always have a
very big lunch. I go to sleep usually
around 4:00, wake up at 7:00,
take a shower, and I always find myself
even in the shower kind of singing or
thinking subconsciously or already in
the performance, have a cup of coffee
and go straight to to the concert hall.
If I can walk to the concert hall,
that's even better. trying to arrive to
the whole as late as possible just so
that you literally you have only time to
change
and you're going on stage.
What I'm trying to do is to avoid human
contact before you're saving your
energy. You're saving your energy for
>> when you learn music. You're learning
what has taken hundreds of years to
accumulate. You've learned knowledge
that goes back to the 15, 16, 17
centuries. All the great musicians that
were before you and all the things
they've learned are inside of you.
>> You go to work and you work is Mozart
and Beethoven [music] and Mer and Fras.
You're dealing with some of the greatest
minds and some of the greatest talents
that ever existed.
>> [applause]
>> It's really a rush, you know, like no
matter what you're playing, no matter
what the audience is, like I could be
performing in front of two people and I
still like feel the rush.
>> The high after a performance is really
indescribable. You know, you feel like
you're on a cloud. It's it's really hard
to come down.
>> So, you have to figure out, you know,
what drives them. You have to figure out
what they see as your mission as an
artist because having a full calendar
and going and performing all over the
world is wonderful, but it sort of tends
to get old very quickly. Trying to
figure out what motivates an artist to
get on that plane for the teams trying
to play the same conterto yet again, you
know, because there's a lot of pressure
in the situation. Before you know it,
you're in front of thousands of people
presenting the result of your work. So,
it's it's really daunting and you have
to find something that makes makes it
all worthwhile.
>> A huge component of mastery is the
social area. You can be technically
brilliant at what you do at playing the
violin, the piano, conducting, but if
you're don't know how to deal with
people, if you have no political skills,
it neutralizes all of your talent and
all of your skill. Nobody wants to hire
you. He [music] has I don't know how
many quotes he like more than 100.
>> Conducting is a vacation to compared to
what actual everyday
life as a as a as a fundraiser PR press
manager.
What was it like being in an orchestra
with the person you're [music] in a
relationship with the that you share a
family with?
>> It's it's great actually in the moment.
It's our only opportunity to spend time
just like we used to do before we got
kids. We are very happy for the moments
we can spend together in the orchestra
>> because we can play together and uh well
yeah [laughter] do all kinds of things
and have parties together and it's very
nice.
You conduct all these big orchestras and
and you inevitably you have this feeling
that you are somehow
sort of in charge and then then you come
and
see your kids, you know, and and you
They don't know
or care frankly
what you do. For them it's important
that I am with them. I'm somehow just
like not even so much talking to them
but just there physically in the same
room. I mean people say it must be
really hard to conduct a concert. You
know, it's a piece of cake to conduct a
concert next to spending a day or even a
half a day with two of my girls. One is
seven, one is nine because the enormous
energy and it's just shared joy of being
alive. It is so unbelievably powerful
that after they I've somehow managed to
calm them down and put them to bed at
night, you feel like you have conducted,
you know, the whole ring cycle. Papa, do
you know if you would bicycle, you know,
from here to moon, do you know how many
days it would take? And it's like what?
How many days would it take if you
bicycle from here to moon? You just
realize that there is an in sort of
parallel intelligence
where all the things that you think you
are mean nothing.
Pavo Yarvy is one very interesting
example of a conductor. He's one of the
few conductors that I feel when I watch
him that he controls the orchestra like
an instrument the way a violinist
controls a violin.
>> Pavo is really dedicated to the music.
He really cares about the music that
he's doing. You can just feel that he's
really alive in the music.
>> [applause]
>> uh all those people who wants to meet
him because there are like thousands.
Everybody wants to audition to him.
Everybody wants to meet him.
Finding the money, finding the partners,
finding the sponsors is a constant
preoccupation for the organization.
>> It takes quite a bit of money for an
orchestra to operate. Most of that money
is raised at night, particularly after
great concerts. If you don't know how to
deal with people, if you don't have
managerial skills, if you don't know how
to influence and get everybody on the
same page, you're going to have a lot of
problems. A conductor, more than
anything, has to be incredibly skilled
at this level of social intelligence.
Everybody else.
It's like Karayan said, you know, that
conducting an orchestra is like jumping
with a horse. You know, you have to set
it up right, but then you have to hold
on and let the horse jump.
I enjoy getting to know different
personalities and every orchestra has
its own personality. It's a big family.
Often we I thought also to to to go
away, you know,
make a little bit more money and but if
it's your family, then you stay.
>> Everybody in this orchestra loves what
they do and is completely
emotionally and intellectually invested
in what they're doing. Everybody is
there with their heart and soul and mind
and it's fantastic. I can't imagine
being anywhere else.
[applause]
>> [music]
[whistles]
[music]
>> We need to have a greater sense of
history. A lot of people, young people
in particular, u are more connected to
to rock music, let's just be honest, or
to hip-hop or to these newer genres of
music, but they're don't they're not
aware that the history of western music
that we listen to all began with
classical music.
>> I used to listen to Bach when we were in
the Beatles. That was probably our
favorite composer then. I like Monty
Verde because I think there's a lot in
common with early Beatle music. You have
to be mindful of the fact that in this
day and age the um number of things that
people are constantly offered in terms
of entertainment, you know, basically
things to do on their Saturday night is
vast and you do have to figure out a way
to make this relevant to them.
>> Whether you like orchestral music or
not, uh if you have an appreciation for
what makes a great city, certainly art
and culture and the creative economy are
part of any great city. Not just in
America, but anywhere in the world.
>> A year after the Honolulu Symphony
declared bankruptcy [music]
and stopped holding concert closed down,
the 110year-old orchestra.
>> Leaders of Louisville's orchestra filed
for bankruptcy. Today, the New Mexico
[music] Symphony Orchestra is going out
of business. Financial trouble for the
orchestra has been a familiar refrain.
>> I don't like have the full knowledge to
be able to appreciate it.
>> It just has become obsolete after a
while because no one really makes it
anymore. I just think people like music
with words.
>> I love 20th century music like WC and
Vince Cryab. They had huge influences on
rock and roll and they are wild music.
>> If you go to a concert once and you
didn't like it. Sorry, I tried. Not my
thing. Never again. Use the same logic
with movies. I went to movies once.
Didn't like the movie. Never again. You
think that you lost your mind?
If your main goal in life is to have a
family,
um, then you probably should not aim for
mastery because it's not conducive. The
two aren't conducive to each other. Your
love is going into your work. But for a
marriage, it's hard to to make that
balance. And the people that can and do
do it are are real masters.
We haven't talked about how you met
Tatiana.
>> I don't want to go too much into it.
>> I can just say a couple of things.
>> Sure.
>> I met Tanya when uh I was in London. She
was still studying in the Royal Academy.
That's just lessons in life, you know,
lessons in life.
You think certain things never happen
will never happen to you and they do.
You know the divorce happens. Um many
other things happen which you either
later regret or don't even understand
how they happen.
Three weeks ago I was very very honored
to be conducting Berlin filmonic and
this week Mais Jansson's a great Latian
conductor cancelled and they called me
said Pavo would you like to come we
would like you to come and you know what
I sat there
I thought for two seconds and said no
I'm I was dying to go there
but I couldn't the the option of not
coming to see the kids of after not
after not seeing [music] them for two
months was simply not possible for me
10 years ago. I probably would have said
yes.
You you live and learn.
[applause]
[cheering]
Jazz is one of the few things that
relaxes me.
If I'm not studying or performing, you
can probably find me listening to jazz.
It's more similar to classical music
than people might imagine.
>> I met Ed at Mos at the jazz club. I was
totally sort of in awe of his music
music making and and he has his um jazz
club that [music] he owns now in a
historic Cincinnati building. It sort of
fits exactly what Edmos is like. you
know, he's he sort of plays when he
wants to and he doesn't play when he
doesn't want to and you has to kind of
show up there and figure out is it is it
going to be on or not?
>> Jesus Christ.
>> He is a wonderful musician and when he
plays he also kind of you feel that
there is no plan even though he knows
exactly what he's doing but it's so
intuitive and it's so incredibly free
and emotional.
>> Let's get in.
Jazz.
>> I love jazz. What are you doing?
>> I do. It's one of my most favorite
[music]
Our
music business is very often so career
oriented and it is so disturbing because
it's all about sort of one level after
another rather than the essence of it
which is music. He's a musician.
All that stuff that surrounds music
[music] business is so unimportant.
Somebody of this caliber is not
universally known. [music]
I admire his perseverance of staying
with music with with still giving it
all. It's all about music and when he
sits he plays and [music] he plays like
a god.
You're the man.
>> I appreciate you.
>> You're the man.
A group needs a kind of transcendent
cause that makes everybody believe that
they're not just sitting there playing
music for this one concert, but they're
creating something beautiful that's even
larger than just them as an individual.
And what a great leader does is they
able to bring everybody to the same
page. They're a uniting force. What
they've learned over the years is that
you're appealing to their greater spirit
in them. That together we can create a
work of art that's just magnificent.
>> The Schnellers 24
>> a great business leader or a great
military leader. He's saying, "You're
not just fighting a war. This is a cause
that we're all fighting for.
It was more difficult in the old days
with the records and all that things.
You um [music] but now it's it's much
easier to be enjoy all kinds of music.
>> In the past without recordings basically
the only way you heard music was either
to go to a performance or make it
yourself. And now we're much more
passive listeners.
>> We have access now to the through the
internet YouTube. You can go on YouTube
and watch old performances, new
performances, everything you want.
>> The music of the past, even several
decades past, fell out of repertoire
immediately. Now we have 400 years of
musical experience that is available
[music] to us both through live
performance and through recordings.
My father, he was like the first
conductor who studied in in abroad so to
speak even though it was part of the
Soviet Union. When he came back to
Estonia at a very young age of like 22
or 23, he was appointed the music
director of the National Orchestra
Estonia,
the opera and the chamber orchestra. In
Soviet Union, we all lived in a kind of
subliminal fear. I remember clearly my
parents really wanting to talk [music]
privately about something political or
whatever. They would go to the bathroom
and turn on the faucets.
as he traveled as a guest conductor,
the Soviet authorities made sure that
the family stays behind as a hostage so
to speak so that my father would then
come back.
They were good friends and when my ar
wrote a piece credo, [music] my father
premiered it.
Credo of course is on a religious text
and in [music] a Soviet situation
religion anything to do with a religious
text were basically banned. It was also
very popular after the first
performance. It was it was [music]
immensely wellreceived and and so my
father was pretty much asked not to
perform it again and he did it anyway.
And after that of course his life became
very difficult in Soviet Union.
>> Are we are we recording?
>> All right. We're doing whatever you want
to go.
>> Dear friends, this is Pabby
director of Front Tra Symphony
Orchestra.
>> Why don't you try it again from the top?
No. Well, I mean, I'm sort of
improvising because he has to be kind of
spontaneous, you know. Okay, I'll try
again. Dear friends, this is Pavo Yarvi,
um, the music director of the Frankfurt
Trader Symphony Orchestra. I would like
to say how much I enjoy coming to Japan
and how much I look forward to coming to
Japan. It is one of those countries that
I feel the audience is most receptive
and knows how to listen and enjoys
serious long deep music.
For me, being music director of more
than one orchestra has very much to do
with the fact that each one has
something unique to offer and I enjoy
variety.
I work with people from all different
countries and I went to school with
people from all different countries
because classical music is extremely
international.
The thing I find most rewarding about
music is connecting with people through
music, connecting with the audience,
connecting with people on stage.
>> Music has the ability to say things in
descriptive detail that you really
wouldn't be able to say at all with
words. You wouldn't be able to come
close, I don't think.
Wait,
what's your name?
>> My name is
>> Long OC. Long time no see. Is it
NHK Symphony Orchestra has chosen a
49year-old Estonian American as its next
chief conductor. Pavo Yarvy has received
several awards during his international
career, including a Grammy,
Henry Kissinger.
negotiated
a deal with Russians
on behalf of Israel to let the Jewish
population of Soviet Union to so-called
reunite their families in Israel. My
mother uh was very clever in sort of
convincing the authorities that she had
a brother in Israel, which of course
she's she's an only child. But but
somehow with her powers of persuasion,
she managed to get permission to leave
Soviet Union and and um reunite our
families in Israel. And once we were in
Vienna, of course, we we we came to
United States.
Being nationalistic
in a country like Estonia where you have
one and a half million people is a way
of survival. It's a if because everybody
have been has been trying to kind of
make our culture obsolete being small
and incredibly proud of our culture and
our language that the nationalism as
such was something that was sort of
part of our existence.
Glor.
It was an extraordinary show of mass
defiance in the Baltic region of the
Soviet Union.
>> There are only one and a half million
people. The army is small,
but we are determined people.
They took away a lot,
but they won't take away music. For us
Estonians, music is important.
Music is powerful. It can start wars and
it can stop them.
>> Mr. Gorbachoff
teared down this wall.
I remember being in the United States
being sort of amazed that this is
actually happening because who would
have ever thought that Soviet Union
would collapse
is actually happening. This is actually
I will actually be able to go back to
Estonia someday and I remember it it
just being just a shock because I knew
by coming to United States that I will
never see this Estonia again.
It's maybe the combination of the
environment, the ease of being in a
wonderful small provincial town which is
just for me the terribly charming uh
beautiful surrounded by water and and
being surrounded by family.
Parano is a place where we spent all our
summers. It is something that
that for us started as a kind of a
natural desire to kind of get everybody
together in our family and combine music
and family.
It also then grew into into this
conducting course because teaching
conducting is a big passion for my
father and I have sort of inherited it.
That's a really important part of
mastery is that ability to have a
mentor, somebody that you can literally
physically observe and absorb their
energy and spirit. You're not just
simply watching them, you're
experiencing them inside yourself. You
need that visceral, human, physical uh
connection. It's a very, very powerful
way of learning.
>> The winner is Mr. Jose Luis Gomez Rios.
>> One of the wonderful things that
happened to me that changed my life out
of being a competition winner was the
fact of working with Pavo because
immediately what happened is that
[music] the uh the orchestra and and
Pavo wanted to have an assistant and
when they saw me he he he was happy. You
can tell that the person has personality
and and that
gift
of communication that that is something
that one cannot learn.
>> It's an emotional relationship that you
have with your mentor. It's somebody
that you respect and admire and that you
could see yourself. I could be that
person.
>> This is [music] a festival that carries
our name. This is the place that gave
birth to us. This is the place that
considers us the kind of a cultural
icons of their country.
>> My father is a great man. He's a legend.
Because of our schedules, I don't get to
see him often.
When I do see him, it's in Estonia. It's
a very special place.
[applause]
He is on one hand the biggest influence
and a mentor I've ever had. Without him,
I would never be a conductor. On the
other hand,
he's my biggest fan.
He's somebody who looks on internet to
see what's written about me and when he
sees something good email me the link
and say congratulations my son I love
you
and this is you know a very famous great
man who could just sort of take anything
for granted but he is a huge
And I want to share it with anyone. If
there is one person in
2,000
people uh audience, I'll be satisfied. I
don't care. It's just we are
communicators.
Music is life
and I couldn't imagine
living without it. It stays with you and
it's it's music it's your companion.
Music [music] it's it's something that
stays all the time.
>> You have to have the guts, the gumption
to realize from within. It can only come
from within. I've learned as much as I
can learn and I need to express myself
now and it's time for me to set out on
my own.
This is my third season as the music
director of Oxar opening in Paris with
the orchestra that is really world class
with live and television. It has to look
good. It has to sound good. It has to
fly off the stage. It's the first
concept of the season. It's also showing
yes we're back.
>> Programming is an art form in itself.
You got to sell tickets. You have to
have the stars. Got to flow certain way.
>> There's 36 million [music] students in
China studying piano alone. When Langl
Long applied for the Beijing
Conservatory, he was one of 3,000 music
[music] students that had gone through
already grueling demands for 12 slots.
To get in requires from age four or
five, a level of dedication, intensity,
focus that is unmatched by any athlete.
>> I I'm a big dreamer. So when I was a
kid, I really wanted to you know become
a musician and somehow uh this drive uh
this inspiration from the music itself
[music] always drive me. We play I for
me very passionate very emotional music.
There's a thin line between what the
audience wants and that that will
challenge [music] the musicians
creatively.
The goal is to find that perfect
balance.
When it comes [music] down to it, it's
the performance. And if you do your job,
people will remember that concert
[music] for the rest of their lives.
Every little bit in this puzzle has to
work.
Now at the end of the day what really
matters is the level of performance.
[music]
It needs to be something that people
forget about everything by listening to
this concert.
>> There comes a point where you're sitting
in a dressing room thinking waiting and
then it hits you. There's no more time.
People are in the seats. They're
waiting. I can feel them. Before the
concert like this, it requires a
tremendous effort. That's why I wait
till the last minute
>> and then
it's game time.
>> Mel is feeling sick and nervous.
Everybody's anxious, but I must remain
calm. The French Minister of Culture is
there is a moment right before you take
the stage. A feeling it's like nothing
else. [cheering]
[cheering]
Conducting
slow, quiet music to me is much more
difficult than conducting big energetic
music because everybody's is in into it.
Everybody's playing
Glory.
>> [singing]
>> God
glory.
What would you like your daughters to
know about their daddy who
has dedicated his life to what we call
music?
I want them to come back to this moment
when they are in Paris with me coming to
my opening concept. Conducting and
knowing that they are there in the
audience makes all the difference to me.
And then when I turn around and I take
applause, everybody's everybody's
clapping and they're waving at me. That
is that's the best feeling in the world
because they don't they don't clap like
hi. And it's like and I'm trying to like
okay
because This is something that I want
them to remember this this these moments
as special moments spent with me and
spend with me through music.
I think that he's hands down one of the
greatest pianist ever. He is also an
amazing personality, but none of that is
as impressive as his share ability to
communicate something really special
when he's at the piano. The audiences in
France, as you know, they are intuitive.
You can feel that they are somehow
involved in they're not passive
listeners.
Heat. Heat.
>> [cheering and applause]
>> When you feel that it's really a
special, something happens.
You literally you feel like a fly off
the stage. I mean you literally have
this feeling that you have wings.
It's the process of the performance that
somehow brought you to this
climax. It's very sexual. It's very
erotic. It's very It's very human.
Miss
In music, we are trapped in time.
Each note is gone as soon as it is
sounded, and it can never be
recontemplated [music]
or heard again in that particular
instant of rightness. It is always too
late for a second look.
The fact that I'm even allowed to do
what I'm doing and that they can
actually even consider it a job, which
of course it's absurd. It's a privilege
is something that I [music] never
thought that I will I will have in my
life.
[music]
[applause]
We live, we die.
Music is what's in between.
>> [cheering and applause]
[applause]
>> Actually
it's classical music is also very you
know beautiful and everything else you
know just like what you feel in the
other fields in music and so people
should open their heart and to feel it
feel it. I cannot imagine that my life
would be sort of emotionally complete
without this music that I love so much.
Um, I think it's very sad that there are
a relatively small number of people that
know this music. You have to listen. You
have to listen carefully.
>> I think one thing that people don't
realize who don't know classical music
is that it's got everything. It's got
humor. It's got fun. It's got excitement
that I think definitely rivals the the a
rock concert as far as even just a pure
physical uh energy that can be created
by a great orchestra or a great soloist.
>> And it happens when you read a great
book or you see a great movie [music]
and you walk out after that and you are
a different person than you were going
into it. everyone can [music] find
something in the arts that helps them
say what they have to say, helps them
really um express their voice, [music]
their individual voice, and um connect
with the greater world around them. A
lot of people
think that they have to have a degree in
[music] classical music in order to be
able to appreciate it. And that's just
not true because you know anybody
anybody you know can be moved to tears
by a really compelling performance of a
Brahms violin conerto.
>> The [music] music is the closest thing
to God literally.
There's no such thing that is closer.
>> Like my son I offer him more of a
structured lifestyle than what I've
experienced. And it allows him to be
like [music] he'll be classically
trained by the time he's 20 years old
because he he takes an hour and a half
and two hours out of the day.
>> For me, that gives me hope. That means
there are a lot of people out there who
love this, who want to be doing it with
their lives. I see a bright future for
for classical music
>> music. It gives you hope for a better
day. Like you could be feeling solo and
you either start playing or you listen
to music and you automatically just feel
better because that's the kind of spirit
it brings with it.
The roots of our music go back to
generation way back in time.
I think it's important to keep this
sense of continuity alive.
Once you're lucky enough to kind of fall
in love with it,
you are never alone because this music
thing sits and lives inside you.
>> [music]
>> Hallelujah.